Chicago Ethnic Arts Project collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 6: Sound Recordings, 1977
  - Subseries 8: South Slavic, Czech, Slovak
    - Life story of Mato Brzovich, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-3, June 03, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20697A - AFS 20698A; RYA 0721-0722; 3 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1-3 of a 3-part interview that concerns the life story of Mato (Matthew) Brzovich, conducted in Croatian; the recording is audible although marred by a 60-cycle hum.
    - Interview with Gordana Trbuhovic-Grasa, leader of Oplenac dance group, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-5, June 05, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20699A - AFS 20701A; RYA 0723-0725; 5 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 5-part interview with Gordana Trbuhovic-Grasa, leader of Oplenac dance group; topics include family background; father is a Serbian priest; about patent's courtship, father's life and education; about the births of children and work in various parishes around the U.S.; how Trbuhovic-Grasa got into folklore; festive events in Chisholm, Minnesota; nationality attitudes to Slovenians and Croatians; the influence of the Duquesne University Tamburitzans; Trbuhovic-Grasa's first dance group on Serbian Day, Kolo Club in San Diego, dance class at Mesa Jr. College, sunmer stock theater; moved to Steelton, Pennsylvania, about teaching the kolo group in Steelton; mention of the eight-volume work on traditional dance titled Narodne Igre (Folk Dances) compiled by the sisters Ljubica and Danica Jankovi? and published in 1934. Part 2 of a 5-part interview with Gordana Trbuhovic-Grasa, leader of Oplenac dance group; topics include comments on the eight-volume work on traditional dance titled Narodne Igre (Folk Dances) compiled by the sisters Ljubica and Danica Jankovi? (1934), continued from part 1; about the dance group in Steelton, Pennsylvania; rehearsing on the street and "colored" kids; then to Pittsburgh to school; ran off and got married; move to Chicago; getting the dance group started at the Russian church, Venetian Night Festival, reorganizing the Serbian Church Choir, about the Oplenac dance group; about relations between various Yugoslav dance troupes; Oplenac and the Avala Orchestra; involvement with DPs (displaced persons); Trbuhovic-Grasa blossoming as a director. Part 3 of a 5-part interview with Gordana Trbuhovic-Grasa, leader of Oplenac dance group; topics in parts 3 and 4 include working with Oplenac; performance in Farrell, Pennsylvania; getting Chicago dancers involved; political hassles for the dance group, varied teaching duties, financial arrangement of dance groups; about Serbian as compared to Yugoslav; the break with the Serbian church; Steve Aleksic becomes manager, how interference from parents related to politics killed the group; the reorganization, Oplenac/American as compared to Slavic members. Part 4 of a 5-part interview with Gordana Trbuhovic-Grasa, leader of Oplenac dance group; topics in parts 3 and 4 include working with Oplenac; performance in Farrell, Pennsylvania; getting Chicago dancers involved; political hassles for the dance group, varied teaching duties, financial arrangement of dance groups; about Serbian as compared to Yugoslav; the break with the Serbian church; Steve Aleksic becomes manager, how interference from parents related to politics killed the group; the reorganization, Oplenac/American as compared to Slavic members. Part 5 of a 5-part interview with Gordana Trbuhovic-Grasa, leader of Oplenac dance group.
    - Interview with Edward Hribar of the Slovene National Benefit Society (SNPJ), Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, June 06, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20702A - AFS 20702B; RYA 0726; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 2-part telephone interview with Edward Hribar of the Slovene National Benefit Society (SNPJ, Slovenska Narodna Podporna Jednota, SNPJ); about the founding of SNPJ in l904; the purpose of the society in the early period, social events of past and present, scholarships and National SNPJ days, National Campsite and Youth Olympics; musical activities for the youth; Grace Dork, the director of Circle 26 on youth group activities; sports, music, dancing; the nationality of SNPJ memberships; publications of SNPJ, elaborated description of publications, including Prosveta, calendars, Voice of Youth. Part 2 of a 2-part telephone interview with Edward Hribar of the Slovene National Benefit Society (SNPJ, Slovenska Narodna Podporna Jednota, SNPJ); about travel to Yugoslavia, membership drive awards, relationship to Yugoslavia, problems of Slovenes in Austria; the Chicano Federation of Lodges, Memorial Day Ceremonies, the organization of picnics, location of the Prosveta (publication) archives.
    - Interview with Mrs. Slavoff of the Balkan Import Store, Chicago, Illinois, June 07, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20703A; RYA 0727; audiocassette, C-60
      Interview with Mrs. Slavoff of the Balkan Import Store; topics include how the Balkan Import Store got started, what the store carries, problems with importing, what sort of phonograph records appeal to what age groups; on newspaper delivery; other nationalities whose records thisa store also carries; about Yugoslav singers who visited the store; television and advertising on the Yugoslav TV show; the geographic range that the store covers, newspapers sent by mail, how they pick out the phonograph records to carry; other items in the store, e.g., postcards, novels.
    - Interview with Josef Barton about Czech and Slovak community activities, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, June 08, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20704A - AFS 20704B; RYA 0728; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 2-part interview with Josef Barton in English about Czech and Slovak community activities; low audio levels. Part 2 of a 2-part interview with Josef Barton in English about Czech and Slovak community activities; low audio levels; duration 2:30 minutes.
    - Interview with Martin Kapugi about tamburitza career, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, June 08, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20705A - AFS 20705B; RYA 0729; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of 2-part interview with Martin Kapugi about tamburitza career; born in Chicago, raised in Europe; father and mother's backgrounds (father from Macedonia; in part 2 states mother was Croatian, father Serbian); Kapugi started to play music 1926, E alto sax, banjo; came to Chicago 1928 alone to his uncle, left mines in West Virginia, found a tamburitza teacher, Art Milacik [Milacek?], a Bohemian; about the repertory in the "old days: as compared to now; there was a Kolo Club during the Depression, had a great time, learned kolos; playing with Vaso Bukvic and Art Milacek [Milacik?]; played with Paul Whiteman's Orchestra; Sloboda Serbian Choir performance, Adam Popovich, Teddy Popovich; about work in Chicago, at the Crane Co.; Tamburitza Café; travel with Dave Zupkovich Orchestra, making recordings for Decca, Victor, Balkan, Zora, Continental; about the importance of Louis Hlad, about bands pressing their own records, about the money in records; then there were newcomers, like the D.P.'s (displaced persons) and American Yugoslavs; they have varied tastes; about his sources for repertory, instrumentals as compared to vocals; about money and music. Part 2 of 2-part interview with Martin Kapugi about tamburitza career; about the music business, 3-4 years with one band, 1931; about venues for music, often played wedding, often for Lithuanians (who like waltzes and slow numbers), mentions female musicians who played bass and cello; about playing in Las Vegas and Los Angeles; Kapugi's mother was Croatian, father Serbian; about selling records at performances.
    - Recording at Pancner's Imports, Berwyn, Illinois, June 09, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20706A; RYA 0730; audiocassette, C-60
      Interview recording made at F. Pancner's import store, 6514 West Cermak Road, Berwyn, Illinois; operated by a Czech family, the store provides Chicago's Czech and Slovak communities with crystal and ceramic ware, folk costume dolls, and other crafts, as well as carrying Czech and Slovak books and records; the interview is with Olga [Mitas? Midas?], has worked at store for 13 years; store had been in the old Czech neighborhood near 26th Street and St Louis Avenue; about Mr. Pancner's annual buying trips to Czech Republic, the store's customers, interest in travel to Czech Republic, about youth and dance groups in Chicago, Moravian groups included, about the merchandise in the store, band recording by artists from Omaha, names other musicians; duration about 9 minutes; photographs of the shop (and presumably the interviewee) at call number AFC 1981/004: b48707, frames 29-37 (digital sequence numbers 30-38).
    - Interview with Slavco Hlad, Berwyn, Illinois, June 10, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20707A; RYA 0731; audiocassette, C-60
      Interview with Slavco Hlad, music store proprietor (Balkan Music Company) and operator of an independent record label, Berwyn, Illinois; Hlad is the son of tamburitza instrument maker Ivan Hlad and Slavco Hlad's business began with instrument making as well; the record label features artisits from the Croatian, Slovenian, Serbian, and Bohemian communities.
    - Recording of performances by the Continentals at the Club Continental on North Lincoln Ave., Chicago, Illinois, part 1-3, June 10, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20708 - AFS 20709, AFS 20711; RXA 1057-1060; 3 audiotape reel, 7 in.
      Part 1 of a 3-part recording of performances by "The Continentals" at the band-owned Club Continental on North Lincoln Ave. (probably 5515 North Lincoln); the fieldworker's notes identify Mitke Kotlarovski as the organist, Blaze Kotlarovski as the guitarist, and other band members by first names, Mince, Koco, and Mike, four of the five immigrated from Resen, Macedonia; the other instruments include drums, accordion, trumpet, bass, and vocals; selections include an unnamed rock song, sung in [South Slavic language]; an unnamed Instrumental in 5/4 time; "The Last Waltz"; "Words"; "Fraulein"; "Johnny and Lydia;" unnamed song in [South Slavic language]; "For Helen," [South Slavic language] lyrics; "Shake Your Boodie;" "Kiss an Angel Good Morning" with strong crowd reaction. Part 2 of a 3-part recording of performances by "The Continentals" at the band-owned Club Continental on North Lincoln Ave. (probably 5515 North Lincoln); the fieldworker's notes identify Mitke Kotlarovski as the organist, Blaze Kotlarovski as the guitarist, and other band members by first names, Mince, Koco, and Mike, four of the five immigrated from Resen, Macedonia; the other instruments include drums, accordion, trumpet, bass, and vocals; selections include "Neither One of us Wants to be the First to Say Goodbye" (recording begins with song in progress); "Wasted Days and Wasted Nights"; "Suspicion;" a Spanish number with rhumba beat; "Words," repeated from part 1, dedicated to a "very special lady;" "Say You'll Stay On 'Til Tomorrow;" [South Slavic language] song, a ballad similar in style to the country ballads played previously; an unnamed mazurka, with singing in [South Slavic language], includes a snatch of the "Song of the Volga Boatmen;" "I'm Sending You a Big Bouquet of Roses;" "Seasons in the Sun;" "Somewhere My Love;" unnamed instrumental. Part 3 of a 3-part recording of performances by "The Continentals" at the band-owned Club Continental on North Lincoln Ave. (probably 5515 North Lincoln); the fieldworker's notes identify Mitke Kotlarovski as the organist, Blaze Kotlarovski as the guitarist, and other band members by first names, Mince, Koco, and Mike, four of the five immigrated from Resen, Macedonia; the other instruments include drums, accordion, trumpet, bass, and vocals; selections include "I Believe in Miracles;" an unnamed [South Slavic language] song not unlike "Never on Sunday;" "Tie a Yellow Ribbon 'Round the Old Oak Tree" (in the recordings, the vocals are lost for long passages); unnamed medium-tempo ballad; song in [South Slavic language]; "Nothing in the World I do Means a Thing Without You;" "Fly Robin, Fly;" "'Til the Next Teardrop Falls;" [South Slavic language] rock tune; "Love Me Tonight;" [South Slavic language] song "For Mr. Balerio and Company," lyrics may have to do with immigration.
    - Interview with members of the Continentals at the Club Continental on North Lincoln Ave., Chicago, Illinois, June 10, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20710; RXA 1059; audiotape reel, 7 in.
      Interviews in [Serbian or Macedonian ?] by fieldworker Richard March with members of "The Continentals" at the band-owned Club Continental on North Lincoln Ave. (probably 5515 North Lincoln); the existing documentation is incomplete but the two interviewees are probably Mitke Kotlarovski (the band's organist) and Blaze Kotlarovski (the band's guitarist); the two immigrated from Resen, Macedonia, in the 1960s; the first interview has a duration of 4:30 minutes, the second has a duration of 10 minutes; the entire recording has a duration of 14:30 minutes.
  - Subseries 9: Ukrainian
    - Interview with artist Michael Huminiak at the School of Ukrainian Folk Arts, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-3, June 07, 1977; June 10, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20712A - AFS 20713A; RYA 0732-0733; 3 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 3-part interview with Michael Huminiak at the School of Ukrainian Folk Arts, conducted in Ukrainian; the first segment of this interview was conducted on June 7, 1977, at about 8 pm the School of Ukrainian Folk Arts, 2353 Iowa Ave., Chicago; about various people who run and instruct at the School; the administrator, wood work, embroidery, weaving, Easter egg ornamentation; Huminiak himself concentrates on painting the ceramic forms; has published 2 workbooks on the subject; born in western Ukraine in 1911, arrived in the US in 1946; now retired, formerly worked in a dental lab; the second segment of the interview recorded on June 10, 1977, at Huminiak's home at 316 Pinecroft St.,Roselle, Illinois, about his folk art school: staff, specialities, purpose and aims of the school; cost of courses offered; sponsorship and subsidies from Ukrainian credit union; Huminiak got interested in this school program upon retirement, a hobby; the school has financial difficulties; his daughter Natalie helps support the work; about the ages of the students; about collaboration with the Ukrainian Museum, Ukrainian Institute of Modern Art; the need to preserve and develop cultural assets; arts schools like his are important and should be established in other Ukrainian communities; about his recent publications on Ukrainian ceramic ornamentation designs; his favorite patterns and the need to retain traditional motifs; his approach to his work; about ceramic trends in the Old Country, production methods, styles; currently popular Trypillian ceramic motifs, origin of same in Chicago; about archeological finding re Trypillian ceramics; motifs must talk and reflect thought; about the difficulty in producing the desired red color; Huminiak's favorable opinion about Ukrainian ceramic decalomania, commercially successful. Part 2 of a 3-part interview with Michael Huminiak at Huminiak's home at 316 Pinecroft St.,Roselle, Illinois, conducted in Ukrainian; Huminiak does not sell his work; about his work areas at home; about geometric designs on ceramics, Hutsul (Hutsullan) ornamentation; current technologies in the Soviet Union; thematic content in contemporary Ukrainian ceramics; fieldworker Carl Fleischhauer asks about the pieces he is photographing for the project (see call numbers AFC 1981/004: b48690, b48718, 120, and 121); Huminiak's pride in the work of his students, who have exhibits of their own; Huminiak reads a versified thank you from a student; more on the difficulties obtaining the desired red color; Hutsulian (Hutsul, Hutsulan) methods and techniques; idea to stage a conference of Ukrainian ceramicists, with a show and sale of works. Part 3 of a 3-part interview with Michael Huminiak at Huminiak's home at 316 Pinecroft St., Roselle, Illinois, conducted in Ukrainian; about the work of Mr. Ivanjuk, wood artisan, excellent work; Huminiak asks fieldworker which of his ceramic pieces are most pleasing; remark on Huminiak's aesthetic approach to the decoration of vases; sound of one of the photoflood lights exploding; end of interview.
    - Interview with instrumental-vocal group Vesely Chasy at their studio, Chicago, Illinois, part 1-2, June 08, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20714A - AFS 20714B; RYA 0734; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Part 1 of a 2-part interview with the instrumental-vocal ensemble Vesely Chasy (the Good Times) at their studio in the back of the home of their group leader, John Steciw, 2022 W. Chicago Ave.; interview in English; recording began about about 10:30 pm; the six members of the ensemble introduce themselves; history of the group; kinds of material they perform, costumes, Ukrainian decorations on the instruments and equipment; about the reaction of the Chicago Ukrainian community to their efforts; about out-of-town venues; composition of original material; ages of the members and their occupations; ethnic origin, only two of the six are of Ukrainian ancestry; about similar groups elsewhere in the US and Canada; about their sound equipment, lighting technician, professional approach to their work. Part 2 of a 2-part interview with the instrumental-vocal ensemble Vesely Chasy (the Good Times) at their studio in the back of the home of their group leader, John Steciw, 2022 W. Chicago Ave.; interview in English; how they view their potential, their future; their second LP is in preparation; the kind of material planned for the record, includes the composition of special songs on political themes relating to dissident movement in Soviet Ukraine; original arrangements; regarding the group's revenue, over 4,000 albums have been sold; their efforts to use best technical know-how available in the production of their recordings, best kind of quality equipment; their engagement at Soyuzivka [resort in 1976 was a breakthrough for them; the older generation still control the Ukrainian organizations in Chicago; concern for their impact, their image; about the reaction of non-Ukrainian audiences to their performances; anecdote about one of their songs with mention of a black woman, and their effort to explain this song to local Chicago audience that included African Americans; how they view the relevance of their work vis-à-vis other Ukrainian cultural and musical phenomena and forms; comment on one of their original song creations relating to middle-class life within the Ukrainian American community, "we're rebels, I guess," recording submitted for a Grammy award; non-Ukrainians find the melodies very appealing and buy their record; anecdote about a hillbillv and his reaction to Ukrainian dancing group: "they are maniacs," three of the ensemble members were born in Europe; how is a Ukrainian band supposed to sound?; about non-Ukrainians in the ensemble; "Just because it's Ukrainian doesn't necessarily make it good, there's gotta be a better standard of excellence," impact on young people; $30,000 worth of equipment; "It's a labor of love."
    - Rehearsal of choir at Saints Volodymyr and Olha Ukrainian Catholic Church, Chicago, Illinois, June 09, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20715A; RYA 0735; audiocassette, C-60
      Recording of one part of a rehearsal by the parish choir at Saints Volodymyr and Olha Ukrainian Catholic Church, at 739 N. Oakley Blvd., Chicago; practice at about 8:15 pm in the church basement hall; choir conducted by Roman Andrushko, who also conducted the Chicago schools orchestra in a concert a few days before this rehearsal; recording features "Our Father" sung in Ukrainian.
    - Recording of bandurist Youth Group, led by Mr. Alex Poszewanyck, Church Hall of St. Vladimir, Chicago, Illinois, June 09, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20716; RXA 1061; audiotape reel, 7 in.
      Recording of a rehearsal of the bandurist youth group, led by Mr. Alex Poszewanyck, at the Church Hall of St. Vladimir; the field documentation does not make clear if this is St. Volodymyr Ukrainian Orthodox Cathedral (probably) or Sts Volodymyr and Olha Ukrainian Catholic Church; the selections are tailored for beginners with the bandura and include an instrumental song; song, with counting of the meter by the leader; three songs and a fragment played by the group; solo song.
    - Interviews with Mary Hrynewych, and with Lubo Maciuk, Chicago, Illinois, part 1. Interview with Lubo Maciuk, Chicago, Illinois, part 2, November 09, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20717A - AFS 20717B; RYA 0736; 2 audiocassette, C-60
      Recording first segment from recording start to 14:30 minutes elapsed time presents an Interview in Ukrainian with Mary (Maria) Hrynewych; the fieldworker's notes state that the interview concerned Hyrnewych's life and the more than 60 dolls she has made, displaying the emblematic costumes of the ethnographic region of Ukraine; recording second segment, from 14:30 to 34:00 elapsed time, presents part 1 of a 2-part interview in Ukrainian with Lubo Maciuk, an active leader of the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America (UCCA); the fieldworker's notes state that the interview concerned various aspects of Ukrainian arts as created in Chicago, associated problems, and other related matters; the fieldworker's notes also mention an interview with Natalie Huminiak, not located when this metadata was compiled. Part 2 of a 2-part interview in Ukrainian with Lubo Maciuk, an active leader of the Ukrainian Congress Committee of America (UCCA), from recording start to 7:00 minutes elapsed time; the fieldworker’s notes state that the interview concerned various aspects of Ukrainian arts as created in Chicago, associated problems, and other related matters; the interview includes added comments by women who were present, probably Mary (Maria) Hrynewych and Natalie Huminiak.
    - Interview with Alfonso Davino, baker, Chicago, Illinois, May 05, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20718A; RYA 0737; audiocassette, C-60
      Interview with Alfonso Davino and friends, recorded at Al's Bakery, 816 S. Loomis St.; Davino discusses Passatella, an Italian tavern game that involves wine ("Boss and Under Boss Game"); about old times in Chicago, street vendors; the Mt. Carmel Fiesta (Annual Feast of Our Lady of Mount Carmel), and other fiestas in Chicago and Italy; about the Taylor Street neighborhood (Little Italy) in old times and with modern changes for the worse; Italian foods, holiday foods; about family and the authority of the older brother; the changing neighborhood; about the Mafia and its constructive aspects.
    - Interview with Frank Zanzo and friends, Chicago, Illinois, May 05, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20718B; RYA 0737; audiocassette, C-60
      Interview-conversation with Frank Zanzo recorded at Al's (Davino) Bakery, 816 S. Loomis St.; Zanzo is 69, born in Chicago, his father from a little town near Naples, Italy; Zanzo father and son both worked for the Burlington Railroad; Zanzo's mother died when he was young and he and his sister benefitted from assistance from Jane Addams's Hull House, not far from where he lived; woman named Helen Meyers (Myers?) worked at Hull House and was especially helpful; Zanzo remembered Addams; Zanzo's friend Fred Angelini brings in a bottle of his homemade wine, made from Zinfandel grapes; brief discussion of wine making.
    - Interview with former U.S. Representative Roland V. Libonati and Mrs. Libonati, Chicago, Illinois, May 07, 1977, AFC 1981/004: AFS 20719A; RYA 0738; audiocassette, C-60